So, people are more afraid of insects than they are of dying.
يخاف الناس الحشرات أكثر من خوفهم من الموت.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
At least, according to a 1973 "Book of Lists" survey
على الأقل وفقًا لإحصاءات "كتاب القوائم" عام 1973
which preceded all those online best, worst, funniest lists that you see today.
قبل ظهور القوائم على الإنترنت لأفضل وأسوء وأطرف الأمور التي نراها اليوم.
Only heights and public speaking
فقط الخوف من المرتفعات والخطابة، هما الشيئين
exceeded the six-legged as sources of fear.
اللذين يخافهما الناس أكثر من الحشرات سداسية الأرجل.
And I suspect if you had put spiders in there,
وأعتقد إننا إذا أضفنا العناكب،
the combinations of insects and spiders would have just topped the chart.
ستتصدرهذه التوليفة من الحشرات والعناكب القائمة.
Now, I am not one of those people.
إلا أنني لست واحدة من هؤلاء الأشخاص.
I really love insects.
في الحقيقة أنا أحب الحشرات.
I think they're interesting and beautiful,
واعتقد أنها جميلة ومثيرة للاهتمام
and sometimes even cute.
وأحيانًا ظريفة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I'm not alone.
ولست الوحيدة.
For centuries, some of the greatest minds in science,
لعدة قرون، بعض من أعظم العلماء،
from Charles Darwin to E.O. Wilson,
من تشارلز دارون وحتى إدوارد أوسبورن ويلسون،
have drawn inspiration from studying some of the smallest minds on Earth.
استلهموا أفكارهم من دراسة أصغر العقول على الأرض.
Well, why is that?
حسنًا، لماذا؟
What is that keeps us coming back to insects?
ما الذي يعيدنا دومًا إلى الحشرات؟
Some of it, of course, is just the sheer magnitude of almost everything about them.
أحد الأسباب بالطبع هو ضخامة كل ما يتعلق بها.
They're more numerous than any other kind of animal.
فأعدادها تفوق أي نوع آخر من الحيوانات.
We don't even know how many species of insects there are,
حتى أننا لا نعرف بالضبط عدد أنواع الحشرات الموجودة،
because new ones are being discovered all the time.
بسبب اكتشاف أنواع جديدة طوال الوقت.
There are at least a million, maybe as many as 10 million.
يوجد على الأقل ما يتراوح بين مليون نوع، وربما 10 ملايين نوع.
This means that you could have an insect-of-the-month calendar
وهذا يعني أنه يمكننا عمل تقويم به حشرة لكل شهر
and not have to reuse a species for over 80,000 years.
دون تكرار أي نوع منها لأكثر من 80,000 سنة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Take that, pandas and kittens!
أي أكثر من الباندا والقطط!
More seriously, insects are essential.
بشكل أكثر جدية، فإن وجود الحشرات أمر أساسي.
We need them.
ونحن بحاجة لها.
It's been estimated that 1 out of every 3 bites of food
يُقدَّر أن ثلث طعامنا
is made possible by a pollinator.
يتم إنباته بواسطة حشرات التلقيح.
Scientist use insects to make fundamental discoveries
يستخدم العلماء الحشرات للتوصل إلى اكتشافات أساسية
about everything from the structure of our nervous systems
عن كل شيء من بنية أنظمتنا العصبية
to how our genes and DNA work.
إلى كيفية عمل الجينات والـ DNA.
But what I love most about insects
ولكن أكثر ما أحبه في الحشرات
is what they can tell us about our own behavior.
هو ما يمكنها اخبارنا به عن سلوكنا.
Insects seem like they do everything that people do.
يبدو أن الحشرات تقوم بكل شيء يقوم به البشر تقريبًا.
They meet, they mate, they fight, they break up.
فهي تتعارف وتتزاوج وتتحارب وحتى تنفصل عن بعضها.
And they do so with what looks like love or animosity.
وتفعل ذلك بشكل قد يبدو حميميًا أو عدائيًا.
But what drives their behaviors is really different than what drives our own,
ولكن ما يوجه سلوكها يختلف كثيرًا عننا.
and that difference can be really illuminating.
ويمكن لهذا الاختلاف أن يكون تنويريًا.
There's nowhere where that's more true
من أوضح المجالات
than when it comes to one of our most consuming interests -- sex.
ما يتعلق بواحدة من أكثر حاجاتنا وهي.. التزاوج.
Now, I will maintain. and I think I can defend,
الآن، سأصحِّح، وسأثبت أيضًا،
what may seem like a surprising statement.
جملة قد تبدو مفاجأة بالنسبة لكم.
I think sex in insects is more interesting than sex in people.
أعتقد أن التزاوج لدى الحشرات مثير للاهتمام أكثر من البشر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the wild variety that we see
والاختلاف الكبير الذي نراه
makes us challenge some of our own assumptions
يجعلنا نعيد التفكير في بعض من افتراضاتنا
about what it means to be male and female.
لمعنى الذكورة والأنوثة.
Of course, to start with,
بالطبع، في البداية،
a lot of insects don't need to have sex at all to reproduce.
كثير من الحشرات لا تحتاج للتزاوج لكي تتكاثر.
Female aphids can make little, tiny clones of themselves without ever mating.
فيمكن لإناث حشرات المن إنتاج نسخ صغيرة من نفسها دون تزاوج على الإطلاق.
Virgin birth, right there.
وهذا مثال على الولادة العذرية.
On your rose bushes.
هناك على أغصان الورد لديك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When they do have sex,
عندما تتزاوج الحشرات،
even their sperm is more interesting than human sperm.
فحتى سائلها المنوي مثير للاهتمام أكثر من السائل المنوي البشري.
There are some kinds of fruit flies
وفي بعض أنواع حشرات الفاكهة
whose sperm is longer than the male's own body.
يكون السائل المنوي للذكر أكبر من جسمه.
And that's important because the males use their sperm to compete.
وهذا مهم، لأن الذكور تستخدم سائلها المنوي للتنافس فيما بينها.
Now, male insects do compete with weapons, like the horns on these beetles.
بالفعل، تتنافس الذكور بالأسلحة، مثل القرون في هذه الخنافس.
But they also compete after mating with their sperm.
ولكنها أيضًا تتنافس بعد التزاوج بالسائل المنوي.
Dragonflies and damselflies have penises that look kind of like Swiss Army knives
حشرات اليعسوب ومقترنات الأجنحة لديها أعضاء ذكرية أشبه السكاكين السويسرية
with all of the attachments pulled out.
بعد فتح وإخراج كافة ملحقاتها.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They use these formidable devices like scoops,
فهي تستخدم هذه الأدوات الضخمة كمجارف
to remove the sperm from previous males that the female has mated with.
لإزالة السائل المنوي للذكور الأخرى التي تزاوجت معها الأنثى.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, what can we learn from this?
فماذا يمكننا أن نتعلم من ذلك؟
All right, it is not a lesson in the sense of us imitating them
حسنًا، لا أقصد درس بمعنى تقليدها
or of them setting an example for us to follow.
أو اتخاذها نموذجًا نتبعه.
Which, given this, is probably just as well.
على الرغم من إمكانية ذلك أحيانًا.
And also, did I mention sexual cannibalism is rampant among insects?
فضلاً عن ذلك، هل ذكرت لكم أن التهام الشريك بعد التزاوج شائع بين الحشرات؟
So, no, that's not the point.
ولكن، لا، ليس هذا ما قصدته.
But what I think insects do,
ولكن ما أعتقده هو أن الحشرات
is break a lot of the rules that we humans have about the sex roles.
تكسر كثير من القواعد لدى البشر عن دور كل فرد حسب نوعه.
So, people have this idea that nature dictates kind of a 1950s sitcom version
يؤمن الجميع أن الطبيعة تفرض فكرة أشبه ببرامج الكوميديا في الخمسينات
of what males and females are like.
فيما يتعلق بتصورهم عن الذكور والإناث.
So that males are always supposed to be dominant and aggressive,
حيث يجب أن يكون الذكر دائمًا مسيطرًا وعدوانيًا،
and females are passive and coy.
والأنثى سلبية وخجولة.
But that's just not the case.
ولكن هذه ليست القضية.
So for example, take katydids,
على سبيل المثال، في الجنادب
which are relatives of crickets and grasshoppers.
وهي قريبة لصراصير الليل والجراد النطاط
The males are very picky about who they mate with,
تكون الذكور انتقائية جدًا لمن تتزاوج معها.
because they not only transfer sperm during mating,
لأنها لا تنقل إليها سائلها المنوي فقط،
they also give the female something called a nuptial gift.
بل تعطي للأنثى ما يعرف بهدية الزواج.
You can see two katydids mating in these photos.
في هذه الصور ترون جندبين أثناء التزاوج.
In both panels, the male's the one on the right,
في كلتا اللوحتين، يظهر الذكر على اليمين
and that sword-like appendage is the female's egg-laying organ.
والزائدة على شكل سيف هي عضو وضع البيض في الأنثى.
The white blob is the sperm,
الكتلة البيضاء هي السائل المنوي،
the green blob is the nuptial gift,
والكتلة الخضراء هي هدية الزواج،
and the male manufactures this from his own body
ويصنع الذكر هذه الكتلة من جسمه
and it's extremely costly to produce.
وهي تستهلك قيمة عالية جدًا لإنتاجها.
It can weigh up to a third of his body mass.
قد يصل وزنها إلى ثلث كتلة جسم الذكر.
I will now pause for a moment and let you think about
والآن سأتوقف للحظة لتفكروا
what it would be like if human men, every time they had sex,
ماذا سيكون الحال إذا قام الذكر في البشر بالشيء نفسه عند كل تزاوج،
had to produce something that weighed 50, 60, 70 pounds.
تقديم هدية تبلغ 50 أو 60 أو 70 رطل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Okay, they would not be able to do that very often.
في الغالب لن يتمكنوا من ذلك.
And indeed, neither can the katydids.
في الحقيقة، لا تستطيع الجنادب فعل ذلك أيضًا.
And so what that means
ولذلك هذا يعني
is the katydid males are very choosy
أن تكون الذكور انتقائية للغاية
about who they offer these nuptial gifts to.
بشأن من تعطيه هذه الهدايا.
Now, the gift is very nutritious,
في الواقع تكون هذه الهدايا مغذية للغاية
and the female eats it during and after mating.
وتأكلها الأنثى أثناء التزاوج وبعده.
So, the bigger it is, the better off the male is,
لذلك، كلما كبر حجم الهدية، كان ذلك أفضل للذكر،
because that means more time for his sperm
لأن هذا يعني أن يحظى السائل المنوي بوقت أطول
to drain into her body and fertilize her eggs.
لدخول جسمها لتلقيح البيض.
But it also means that the males are very passive about mating,
ولكن هذا أيضًا يعني أن الذكور سلبية جدًا بشأن التزاوج،
whereas the females are extremely aggressive and competitive,
في حين أن الإناث عدائية وتنافسية للغاية
in an attempt to get as many of these nutritious nuptial gifts as they can.
للحصول على أكبر قدر من هدايا التزاوج المغذيِّة.
So, it's not exactly a stereotypical set of rules.
لذا، لا توجد قواعد نمطية تمامًا.
Even more generally though,
حتى بشكل عام أكثر،
males are actually not all that important in the lives of a lot of insects.
لا تعد الذكور مهمة فعليًا في حياة كثير من الحشرات.
In the social insects -- the bees and wasps and ants --
في الحشرات الاجتماعية، مثل النحل والدبابير والنمل،
the individuals that you see every day --
أفراد هذه الحشرات التي ترونها يوميًا،
the ants going back and forth to your sugar bowl,
أفراد النمل التي تغدو وتروح على طبق السكر،
the honey bees that are flitting from flower to flower --
ونحل العسل الذي يرفرف من زهرة إلى أخرى،
all of those are always female.
دائمًا ما تكون كل هذه الحشرات إناثًا.
People have had a hard time getting their head around that idea for millennia.
عانت البشرية لآلاف السنين محاولة فهم هذه الفكرة.
The ancient Greeks knew that there was a class of bees, the drones,
عرف قدماء الأغريق بوجود فئات من النحل، النحل الطنان،
that are larger than the workers,
التي يكبر حجمها عن النحل العامل،
although they disapproved of the drones' laziness
على الرغم من استهجانهم لكسل النحل الطنان
because they could see that the drones just hang around the hive
لأنهم لاحظوا بقائها حول الخلية فقط
until the mating flight --
حتى موعد طيران التزاوج --
they're the males.
لأنها الذكور.
They hang around until the mating flight,
فتبقى حول الخلية لحين موعد التزاوج،
but they don't participate in gathering nectar or pollen.
ولكنها لا تشارك في جمع الرحيق أو حبوب اللقاح.
The Greeks couldn't figure out the drones' sex,
لم يتمكن الأغريق من التعرف على جنس هذا النحل.
and part of the confusion was that they were aware of the stinging ability of bees
ورجع جزء من حيرتهم إلى معرفتهم بقدرة النحلات على اللدغ،
but they found it difficult to believe
ولكن كان من الصعب عليهم تصديق
that any animals that bore such a weapon could possibly be a female.
أن الإناث في أي نوع من الحيوانات يمكنها حمل مثل هذا السلاح.
Aristotle tried to get involved as well.
حتى أرسطو حاول التدخل أيضًا.
He suggested, "OK, if the stinging individuals are going to be the males ..."
فقد اقترح أن يكون النحل الذي يلدغ ذكرًا،
Then he got confused, because that would have meant
ولكنه وقع في حيرة لأن هذا يعني
the males were also taking care of the young in a colony,
رعاية الذكور أيضًا للصغار في الخلية
and he seemed to think that would be completely impossible.
وقد بدا له هذا مستحيلاً تمامًا.
He then concluded that maybe bees had the organs of both sexes
ثم استنتج إمكانية وجود أعضاء الجنسين معًا
in the same individual,
في نفس النحلة
which is not that far-fetched, some animals do that,
والذي لم يكن مستبعدًا، لأنه موجود في بعض الحيوانات،
but he never really did get it figured out.
ولكنه لم يتوصل أبدًا للحقيقة.
And you know, even today, my students, for instance,
وحتى اليوم، بعض من تلامذتي مثلاً
call every animal they see, including insects, a male.
يعتبرون كل حيوان يرونه، حتى الحشرات، ذكورًا
And when I tell them that the ferocious army-ant soldiers
وعندما أخبرهم أن جنود نمل الجيش الشرسين
with their giant jaws, used to defend the colony,
التي تمتلك فكين كبيرين للدفاع عن المستعمرة
are all always female,
دائمًا ما يكونوا إناثًا،
they seem to not quite believe me.
لا يبدو أنهم يصدقونني تمامًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And certainly all of the movies -- Antz, Bee Movie --
وبالتأكيد كل الأفلام مثل "Antz" و"Bee Movie"
portray the main character in the social insects as being male.
تصوِّر الشخصية الرئيسية في الحشرات الاجتماعية على أنها ذكر.
Well, what difference does this make?
حسنًا، ما الفرق الذي قد يشكله هذا؟
These are movies. They're fiction.
إنها مجرد أفلام خيالية
They have talking animals in them.
تصوِّر الحيوانات على أنها تتكلم.
What difference does it make if they talk like Jerry Seinfeld?
ما الفرق إذا جعلوها تتكلم مثل "جيري سينفيلد"؟
I think it does matter,
لكنني أعتقد أن ذلك يصنع فرقًا،
and it's a problem that actually is part of a much deeper one
وأنها هذه مشكلة تمثِّل جزءًا من مشكلة أخرى أعمق
that has implications for medicine and health
لها تبعاتها على مجال العلاج والصحة
and a lot of other aspects of our lives.
وعلى جوانب كثيرة أخرى من حياتنا.
You all know that scientists use what we call model systems,
فكما تعلمون يستخدم العلماء ما يدعى "أنظمة نموذجية"،
which are creatures -- white rats or fruit flies --
وهي كائنات مثل: الفئران البيضاء أو ذباب الفاكهة،
that are kind of stand-ins for all other animals, including people.
التي تمثِّل الحيوانات الأخرى، بما فيهم البشر.
And the idea is that what's true for a person
والفكرة أن ما يصلح للبشر
will also be true for the white rat.
يصلح أيضًا للفأر الأبيض.
And by and large, that turns out to be the case.
وإلى حدٍ كبير، يكون الوضع كذلك بالفعل
But you can take the idea of a model system too far.
ولكن يمكن أن نأخذ فكرة النظام النموذجي إلى أبعد من ذلك.
And what I think we've done,
وباعتقادي ما فعلناه هو
is use males, in any species, as though they are the model system.
أننا استخدمنا الذكور، في أي نوع، وكأنهم النظام النموذجي.
The norm.
الشكل الطبيعي.
The way things are supposed to be.
الشكل المفترض للنوع.
And females as a kind of variant --
والإناث كصورة مختلفة من النوع،
something special that you only study after you get the basics down.
حالة خاصة نتطرق لدراستها فقط بعد دراسة الصورة الأصلية.
And so, back to the insects.
وهكذا، بالرجوع للحشرات.
I think what that means
أعتقد أن هذا يعني
is that people just couldn't see what was in front of them.
أن البشر لم يتمكنوا من رؤية الحقيقة الواقعة أمامهم.
Because they assumed that the world's stage was largely occupied by male players
بسبب افتراضهم أن العالم يحكمه أغلبية من الذكور
and females would only have minor, walk-on roles.
وأن الإناث مجرد أقلية تقوم بأدوار صغيرة.
But when we do that, we really miss out on a lot of what nature is like.
ولكن إذا فكرنا بهذه الطريقة، فإننا سنغفل كثير من جوانب الطبيعة.
And we can also miss out on the way natural, living things, including people,
كما سنغفل أيضًا الطريقة التي يمكن بها للكائنات الحية في الطبيعة، بما فيها البشر،
can vary.
أن تختلف.
And I think that's why we've used males as models in a lot of medical research,
وأعتقد أن هذا هو سبب استخدام الذكور كنماذج في كثير من الأبحاث الطبية،
something that we know now to be a problem
الأمر الذي نعلم حاليًا أنه يمثل مشكلة
if we want the results to apply to both men and women.
إذا أردنا تطبيق النتائج على الرجال والنساء.
Well, the last thing I really love about insects
حسنًا، الأمر الأخير الذي أحبه في الحشرات
is something that a lot of people find unnerving about them.
هو شئ يخيف كثير من الناس منها،
They have little, tiny brains
امتلاكها عقولاً صغيرة
with very little cognitive ability, the way we normally think of it.
مع قدرات إدراكية محدودة، وفقًا لتفكيرنا.
They have complicated behavior, but they lack complicated brains.
فسلوك الحشرات معقَّد، ولكن عقولها ليست معقدة.
And so, we can't just think of them as though they're little people
لذلك، لا يمكننا تشبيههم بالصغار من البشر
because they don't do things the way that we do.
لأنهم لا يقومون بالأمور بنفس طريقتنا.
I really love that it's difficult to anthropomorphize insects,
في الحقيقة أحب صعوبة تشخيص الحشرات في صورة بشر،
to look at them and just think of them like they're little people
صعوبة النظر إليها وتخيلها كبشر صغار
in exoskeletons, with six legs.
لها هياكل خارجية وستة أرجل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Instead, you really have to accept them on their own terms,
بدلاً من ذلك، يجب عليك تقبلها كما هي،
because insects make us question what's normal and what's natural.
لأن الحشرات تجعلنا نتساءل عن الفرق بين ما هو عادي وما هو جزء من الطبيعة.
Now, you know, people write fiction and talk about parallel universes.
وكما تعرفون يكتب الناس الآن قصصًا خيالية ويتكلمون عن وجود أكوان موازية.
They speculate about the supernatural,
ويخمنون بشأن الأمور الخارقة للطبيعة
maybe the spirits of the departed walking among us.
وحول إمكانية سير أرواح الموتى بيننا.
The allure of another world
الجاذبية الذي يتمتع بها العالم الآخر
is something that people say is part of why they want to dabble in the paranormal.
حسب ما يقولونه، تعد جزءًا من رغبتهم في تفسير هذه الأمور الخارقة.
But as far as I'm concerned,
ولكن على قدر اهتمامي بالأمر
who needs to be able to see dead people,
من قد يرغب في رؤية أرواح الموتى
when you can see live insects?
عندما يمكنه رؤية الحشرات الحية؟
Thank you.
شكرًا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)